<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>I Broke My Kernel: A Tale of Impatience - Shivaraj&apos;s Blog</title>
    <link>https://blog.shivaraj110.com</link>
    <description>Let me tell you about the time I decided to reboot my machine while it was updating packages. Spoiler: it didn&apos;t end well.

 The Mistake

It was late. I was tired. My system was running a routine package update, and I thought, &quot;How long can this possibly take?&quot; Famous last words.

I hit reboot. T...</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 16:40:30 GMT</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://blog.shivaraj110.com/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <managingEditor> (Shivaraj)</managingEditor>
    <item>
      <title>I Broke My Kernel: A Tale of Impatience</title>
      <link>https://blog.shivaraj110.com/post/i-broke-my-kernel</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.shivaraj110.com/post/i-broke-my-kernel</guid>
      <description>Let me tell you about the time I decided to reboot my machine while it was updating packages. Spoiler: it didn&apos;t end well.

 The Mistake

It was late. I was tired. My system was running a routine package update, and I thought, &quot;How long can this possibly take?&quot; Famous last words.

I hit reboot. The ...</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[
Let me tell you about the time I decided to reboot my machine while it was updating packages. Spoiler: it didn't end well.

## The Mistake

It was late. I was tired. My system was running a routine package update, and I thought, "How long can this possibly take?" Famous last words.

I hit reboot. The screen went black. And then... emergency mode. That beautiful red text greeting me like an old friend who's disappointed in my life choices.

## What Actually Happened

When you update packages on Linux, especially on a rolling release like Arch, the kernel and its modules get updated together. Rebooting mid-update means you end up with a partially updated kernel - some files are new, some are old, and none of them want to work together.

The system couldn't mount properly. Systemd threw its hands up. I was staring at a blinking cursor in emergency mode, questioning every decision that led me here.

## The Recovery

First, I tried the obvious - booting into the fallback initramfs. No luck. The kernel was too corrupted for that.

Next step: boot from a live USB. I always keep one around for exactly these moments (read: my frequent mistakes).

After chrooting into my system:

```bash
mount /dev/nvme0n1p2 /mnt
mount /dev/nvme0n1p1 /mnt/boot
arch-chroot /mnt
```

I checked what kernels were available:

```bash
pacman -Q | grep linux
```

The main kernel was in a broken state. Time for the LTS kernel - the boring, stable, "I won't break on you" option that I should've been using all along.

```bash
pacman -S linux-lts linux-lts-headers
```

Regenerated the initramfs:

```bash
mkinitcpio -P
```

Updated GRUB to recognize the new kernel:

```bash
grub-mkconfig -o /boot/grub/grub.cfg
```

Rebooted. Selected linux-lts from the GRUB menu. And finally - my desktop. Beautiful, functional, boring desktop.

## Lessons Learned

Here's what I took away from this adventure:

- **Never reboot during updates.** Just don't. Go make coffee. Touch grass. Do anything except hit that reboot button.
- **Keep a live USB handy.** It's saved me more times than I'd like to admit.
- **The LTS kernel exists for a reason.** It's not exciting, but it's stable. For a daily driver, that matters.
- **Timeshift or snapper snapshots.** I didn't have them configured. I do now.

## Current Setup

I'm now running the LTS kernel as my default, with the mainline kernel as a fallback option in GRUB. The irony isn't lost on me - the "fallback" is now the bleeding edge one.

```bash
$ uname -r
6.12.10-lts
```

Is it as exciting as running the latest kernel? No. Does my system boot every single time? Yes. I'll take that trade.

## Final Thoughts

Breaking your system is a rite of passage for any Linux user. It's how you learn. It's how you understand what's actually happening under the hood instead of just accepting that things work.

That said, maybe don't break it at 2 AM when you have work the next morning. Learn from my mistakes.

Keep calm and always have a backup kernel.
]]></content:encoded>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <category>Linux</category>
      <category>Kernel</category>
      <category>Arch</category>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>